[Music]
all food of animal origin contains
hormones but most of our dietary
exposure to hormones comes from dairy
products by quantity it's mostly
prolactin corticosteroids and
progesterone but there are also a bunch
of estrogens which then concentrate
further when you make other dairy
products like five times more
concentrated in cream and cheese uh 10
times more hormone concentration in
butter so when it comes to exposure to
steroid hormones in the food supply
about 3/4 of our exposure to ingested
female sex steroids comes from dairy
with the rest evenly split between eggs
and meat and fish eggs contribute about
as much as all meat put together which
makes a certain amount of scense since
it comes straight from my hen's ovary
right among the various types of meat
you get as much from white meat fish and
poultry as you do from pork and beef and
this is just from natural hormones not
added hormone injections like Bine
growth hormone so for these it doesn't
matter if the meats organic animals
produce hormones because they're animals
which understandably ends up in animal
products but only about half of people
surveyed seem to know that that lacking
basic knowledge like not realizing what
milk is for cows only give milk after
having a cal so these researchers
suggested we ought to inform the public
about Dairy production practices to
which one Journal of dairy science
respondent wrote you know telling the
public all our new technologies like
transgenic animals meaning genetically
engineered farm animals or taking away
that calf right away so we can have more
the milk or not letting cows see grass
may not actually result in high rates of
public approval so xay on the education
nay one thing with potential Public
Health implications that the public may
not know about is their exposure to
estrogen through intake of commercial
milk produced from pregnant cows see
modern genetically improved dairy cows
such as the Holstein your standard black
and white cow can get re-impregnation
after giving birth and lactate
throughout almost her entire next
pregnancy which means that commercial
cows milk these days contains large
amounts of pregnancy hormones like
estrogens and
progesterone here's the estrogen levels
in milk during the first 8 months of a
pregnant cow's 9month gestation hormone
levels shoot up more than 20 fold but
even so we're still only talking about a
millionth of a gram per quart easily 10
to 20 times less estrogen hormones than
uh what you'd find in like a birth
control pill so would it really have an
effect on human hormone levels drinking
it here are the average levels of three
different estrogens and a progesterone
metabolite flowing through the bodies of
seven men who then proceeded to drink
about a liter of milk within hours their
hormone levels shot
up here are the average levels of these
female sex steroids flowing through the
bodies of six school children average
age eight before before drinking about
two cups of milk and then after within
hours their levels shut up tripling or
quadrupling their Baseline hormone
levels someone can imagine the effects
milk might have on men or or
prepubescent children but what about
women presumably they have such high
levels of estrogens in their body in the
first place well not all women what
about postmenopausal women and
endometrial cancer for example estrogens
have a role in the development of
endometrial cancer which is a cancer of
the lining of the uterus milk and dairy
products are a source of steroid
hormones and growth factors that might
have these kinds of effects so Harvard
researchers followed tens of thousands
of women and their Dairy consumption for
decades and found significantly higher
risk of endometrial cancer among
postmenopausal women who consumed more
Dairy what about dietary exposure to
hormones and breast cancer
unfortunately understanding the role of
dietary hormone exposure in the
population burden of breast cancer is
not possible at this time
[Music]